bulb.co.uk 2019-12-22

# Bulb Privacy Policy | Bulb

## Introduction

We know that providing personal information is an act of trust and we take that seriously.

This Privacy Policy should help you work out what we collect your data for and how we protect it for you. If you have any questions or would like to make any requests about your personal information such as opting out of marketing, please email [privacy@bulb.co.uk](mailto:privacy@bulb.co.uk).

We go into more detail later on this page, but here's the short and sweet version:

## In a nutshell

Most of the data we collect and hold about you is for the purpose of:

  * providing your energy

  * providing you with carbon offsets to balance your CO2e emissions, if you're using our [Carbon Calculator](https://bulb.co.uk/carbon-calculator/)

  * collecting payments from you for the energy efficiency measures you’ve installed on your premises if you’re involved in the Green Deal Plan

We also use data to make Bulb's products and services better, and to help us advertise Bulb.

### To supply you with energy

We gather information about you and your home so we can accurately supply your energy. For example, we need to know your address to supply the right property, and we need to know how much energy you use so we can send you accurate bills.

Where necessary, we share this with other organisations in the energy industry, like your old supplier, Ofgem and the organisations that maintain the national energy databases.

### To supply you with carbon offsets

If you use our [Carbon Calculator](https://bulb.co.uk/carbon-calculator/) to offset your CO2e emissions, we gather information from you so we can work out the size of your carbon footprint and how you can reduce it. 

For example, we need to know what sort of transport you use during the week, the sorts of food you eat and how often you fly, so that we can either provide you with advice on how to reduce your carbon footprint or we will provide you with an option to pay to offset your CO2e emissions.

### To manage your Green Deal Plan ** **

If you are part of the Green Deal Plan, we gather information from about the energy supply at your home, so we can manage your Green Deal Plan. 

### To make Bulb better

We collect data on how you use our website, App and other features. We track things like where you click on our site and what features you use. This lets us learn what's working well and what features we need to improve.

We sometimes share this data in an aggregated form with agencies or partners that are helping us. For example, we might tell a telecommunications partner how many phone calls we get a week.

### To advertise Bulb

We use your data to help grow Bulb and spread renewable energy. If you're a member of Bulb or use our [Carbon Calculator](https://bulb.co.uk/carbon-calculator) to offset your CO2e emissions, we share data with social media, search engines, and other advertising platforms so that we stop asking you to join Bulb or use our Carbon Calculator, and instead show you content more relevant to you.

We also share aggregated data with agencies that help us with advertising. For example, we might share with an agency how many of our members live in Scotland.

### To communicate with you

In addition to sending you key information about your account by email, from time to time we'll also send you information about things we think will interest you. If you're a Bulb member, this includes letting you know the carbon emissions you're avoiding each year by being with Bulb, updates on our referral programme, and reminding you about how you can manage your energy online. 

If you use our [Carbon Calculator](https://bulb.co.uk/carbon-calculator), this includes letting you know what carbon offset projects we are supporting, telling you about new product updates and reminding you that you are approaching the yearly anniversary date for the carbon offsets you have purchased. If you have a Green Plan, this includes letting you know how much you’ve already paid and information on your repayment plan. 

Where necessary, we share your data with organisations that send communications on our behalf. For example, we ask Trustpilot to send invitations to our members and Carbon Calculator users to review Bulb.

## Information we collect from Bulb members

### Information you provide us at sign-up

  * Contact information: such as your name, address, email address, date of birth and telephone number.

  * Vulnerability information: such as disabilities, age, or health conditions for you or a member of your household. This helps us provide suitable [additional services](https://help.bulb.co.uk/hc/en-us/articles/115001233052-What-support-services-does-Bulb-offer-to-our-members-).

  * Financial information: such as your payment details and financial circumstances. We need your bank details if you want to pay by Direct Debit. If you have difficulty paying our bills, providing details of your circumstances helps us work with you to resolve this.

  * If you are eligible for the Feed-in Tariff scheme: additional information to confirm your identity (such as a copy of your passport or driving licence, or proof of company registration) and information about your Feed-in Tariff installation (such as a certification document and your installation meter details). We are required to collect this information to comply with Ofgem's Feed-in Tariff scheme.

## Information we collect from Carbon Calculator users 

### Information you provide us at sign-up

  * Contact information: such as your name, email address and postcode. 

  * Carbon emissions information: such as the type of transport you use during the week, the sorts of foods you eat and how often you fly.  

## Information we collect while we provide you energy services

  * Information about your energy supply: such as your meter reference numbers and meter type. This ensures we link you with the right meter and keep industry databases accurate.

  * Energy you use: such as details of your energy use and your supply start and end dates. If you have a smart meter or Bulb energy monitor we will take consumption data directly from your meter in line with the consents you have given us. We need details of your energy usage so we can send you accurate bills.

  * Energy you generate: details of energy you generate under the Feed-In Tariff scheme or under our Export Tariff. We need this information so we can accurately calculate the payments due to you.

  * Smart meter information: if you have a smart meter it will transmit data that lets us know that it is safe and operating and recording correctly.

  * Warm Home Discount and Affordable Warmth measures: if you apply for the [Warm Home Discount](https://help.bulb.co.uk/hc/en-us/articles/115001245512-The-Warm-Home-Discount) or Affordable Warmth measures, you will be asked for information about any benefits you receive and money you get from employment, to assess your eligibility for assistance. We are required to collect this information to comply with Ofgem's Warm Home Discount scheme.

## Information we collect while we provide you energy services or carbon offsetting services

  * Customer service data: when you get in touch by phone, email, chat or community posts we monitor, record and review those communications so we can provide the best possible service to you, all our members and Carbon Calculator users, and so we can show evidence of transactions or events.

  * Data about your interactions with us: such as information about how you communicate with us (by phone, emails, or chat) and how you use our website and App or interact with our ads and content on other websites. More detail is set out in our Cookie Policy.

  * Technical data: such as IP addresses (including the general information in such address, such as city, county and postcode), login details and other information about your mobile devices, browser types and browser language. More detail is set out in our Cookie Policy.

## Information provided by others so we can provide energy services

Affiliates and partners: when you sign-up with Bulb through an affiliate or partner (such as a price comparison website, a telephone sales agency, an events sales agency or door to door agency) for energy services, we are sent your personal information from that partner so we can enter into a contract with you.

Energy industry partners: metering and debt information can come from other organisations involved in supplying your energy, such as your old supplier and meter operators.

Landlords and estate agents: data such as your name and contact details may be provided to us by people moving in or out of a property you're occupying, or a landlord or estate agent. We may use this information to contact you in relation to the continuation of the energy supply to your property.

Councils, postal services, and data brokers: information such as contact details, homemoving status and other details about your circumstances can be provided by councils, postal services and data brokers. We will always check that these organisations have your consent or are otherwise legally permitted to share this information.

Referrers: data such as your name and contact details may be provided to us by people referring you to Bulb as part of our Referral Programme. We may use this information to contact you in relation to becoming a Bulb member.

Green Deal database: if you have a Green Deal Plan, we will collect information from the Green Deal database to find out who your Green Deal Provider is, your Green Deal ID number, your Green Deal Plan start and end date and your daily charge amount. 

## How we use this information

It's important that you understand what we'll do with the data that we hold about you, as well as the lawful reasons we are allowed to do this.

We may sometimes combine information that we collect from you with information we obtain about you from third parties and affiliates and information derived from any other subscription, product, or service we may provide.

We use the information we hold about you for the following purposes:

### Performing our energy contract with you

We need to process information in order to supply your energy and the services you've asked for under our energy contract. For example, we may use your information (such as your contact information) to organise your switch to Bulb, to take monthly payments and organise meter repair jobs. If you have a Green Deal Plan, we need to process information about you (consumption data, contact information) and your plan so that we can collect payments from you so we can perform your contract with your Green Deal Provider.

### Performing our carbon offset contract with you 

We need to process information in order to provide you a way to offset your CO2e emissions and the services you’ve asked for under our carbon offsetting contract. For example, we may use your information (such as your contact information) to let you know that you have purchased carbon offsets to balance your CO2e emissions for the year, tell you about the carbon offset projects your money has gone towards and remind you when your yearly anniversary date is approaching since you bought your carbon offsets. 

### If we provide you with energy, fulfilling our legal and regulatory energy obligations

Many of the ways we manage your energy are based on requirements set out in our Licence and by Ofgem directions and Codes, such as how we set out your annual statement and how we deal with disputes. 

### Fulfilling our general legal obligations

We may also need to comply with court orders, and disclose information to law enforcement agencies where we are obliged to do so.

### If we provide you with energy, adding you to our Priority Services Register with your consent

If you have let us know that you (or a member of your household) need extra care or are in a vulnerable situation, we will ask for your explicit consent before we add your details to our [Priority Service Register](https://help.bulb.co.uk/hc/en-us/articles/115001233052-What-support-services-does-Bulb-offer-to-our-members-). This helps us take steps to ensure your safety.

### If we provide you with energy, taking your smart meter readings with your consent

If you have a smart meter, we'll normally collect readings from your smart meter once a day. You can decide whether we take a reading for the entire 24-hour period or for each half-hour period. We won't take more than one reading a day unless you have given us your consent. If you'd prefer us to only take one reading a month, you can email us at [privacy@bulb.co.uk](mailto:privacy@bulb.co.uk).

### If we provide you with energy, analysing your smart meter readings to offer you new products and services with your consent

If you have a smart meter, we could use your smart meter readings to understand how you use your energy. For example, we could learn how to buy energy for lower prices and be able to build and offer you new products and services. We will only use your smart meter readings to do this if you have given us your consent. You can email us at [privacy@bulb.co.uk](mailto:privacy@bulb.co.uk) at any time to withdraw this consent.

### For our legitimate business interests

This means that using your information is necessary for us to build our business and provide our services to you. We consider and balance any potential impact on you and your rights before we process your personal data for our legitimate interests. Our legitimate interests include:

  * Maintaining and improving our services: for example, we may use your information that we obtain through your emails and calls to train our team. We may also use your information to ensure that our services are working as intended – for example, understanding which parts of the website are easiest to use. We may also contact you for suggestions on how we can improve the way we provide our services to you.

  * Providing personalised services, including suggested payment amounts: for example, if we provide you with energy, we may use information such as your account balance and expected annual energy use to make an automatic adjustment to your payment amount.

  * If you use our [Carbon Calculato](https://bulb.co.uk/carbon-calculator)r, we may use your information such as the amount of CO2e emissions you offset last year as an indicator of what your carbon footprint may be the following year and suggest that you offset a similar amount of CO2e emissions. We may also provide you with information so that you can compare your carbon footprint with other people in your area. 

  * Providing personalised advertising: we may let advertising platforms like Facebook and Google know that you are a member of Bulb or that you use our Carbon Calculator by sharing your contact details with them. This means we can stop asking you to join Bulb once you're with us, or stop asking you to try our Carbon Calculator, and instead share information with you that we think you might be interested in.

  * Communicating with you about our services: we may contact you about Bulb news, product updates and new products that we think you might be interested in. We may also contact you to provide you with offers, competitions, marketing materials and other promotional materials, both online and through other marketing channels, such as third party social networks, like Facebook. We do not contact our members with marketing messages through SMS or direct messaging via social media.

  * Measuring our performance and developing new services: for example, we use data for measurement to understand how our services are used. We also use aggregated data to understand our members and their energy usage better, or, if you use our Carbon Calculator, to understand the carbon footprint of our users. This helps us develop offerings such as our Annual Impact Report.

  * Helping to prevent and detect fraud or debt: we also need to be able to detect and prevent fraud and recover unpaid energy bills.

If you have questions about the lawful basis on which we collect and use your information, you can email our Data Protection Officer at [dpo@bulb.co.uk](mailto:dpo@bulb.co.uk).

## Sharing your information

### When we share your information

We sometimes need to allow our service providers to process personal information we hold about you on our behalf for the reasons set out in this Policy or as otherwise required by law.

We make sure that these third parties won't use your personal data for their own purposes (unless we have specifically stated in this policy otherwise) and we only permit them to use it in accordance with our instructions and the law. This includes the following types of organisations:

  * Trusted businesses or persons: who process your information for us for the purposes set out above, based on our instructions and as set out in our Privacy Policy and any other appropriate confidentiality and security measures. For example, we use service providers to help us with member support or payment processing.

  * Energy industry partners (if we provide you with energy): including other suppliers, network operators and energy market administrators.

  * Payment providers: we work with payment providers to process your payments. If we provide you with energy, we use [GoCardless](https://gocardless.com/en-eu/legal/privacy/) to process your direct debit payments, [Stripe](https://stripe.com/gb/privacy) to process your debit card payments and [Transferwise](https://transferwise.com/privacy-policy) to process other payments to you (such as under the Feed-in Tariff or for referrals if you have a prepayment meter). You can find more information on how these providers process your personal data and your data protection rights by looking at their privacy policies at the links above.

  * Marketing agencies, search engines and social media networks: to advertise Bulb and to gather feedback on Bulb such as through customer surveys.

  * People you have authorised us to share data with (if we provide you with energy): such as family members, energy brokers, solicitors and debt management companies, so we can fulfil your requirements.

  * Market regulators (if we provide you with energy): such as Ofgem and consumer protection organisations such as the Energy Ombudsman, where we are obliged to do so under regulations.

  * Price comparison sites and other affiliates (if we provide you with energy): if you have signed up to Bulb using a price comparison site or via an affiliate link. We then provide the affiliate with your personal data such as your email address, only to the extent that we can fulfil a contract you have requested.

  * Credit reference agencies (such as Experian) (if we provide you with energy): We may tell credit reference agencies how you're managing your account and whether you owe us money. These agencies can help us trace you if you have moved and we owe you money or you owe us money. More information is set out in [Experian's Credit Reference Agency Information Notice](https://www.experian.co.uk/crain/index.html#question14).

  * People you are referring to Bulb so we can provide them with energy: if you refer a new member to us, we may share your name and aggregated data about your energy use with the referred person.

  * Samsung: if you are a Bulb member and you have chosen to sign up to Samsung’s SmartThings App in order to view your Bulb energy usage and pricing data. We then provide Samsung with that data. Samsung will use personal data in accordance with its own privacy policy which will be presented to you in the SmartThings App.

  * Post Office: if you are eligible for a Warm Home Discount and Affordable Warmth Measures and you are a prepayment member, we may share your name and postal address with the Post Office so that the Post Office can verify your identity when you collect your credit. 

  * Green Deal providers: if you have a Green Deal plan, we may share your information with your Green Deal provider so that we can pay them for the energy efficiency measures you have purchased or where necessary, the UK government to show our compliance with the scheme. 

### When you share your own information

Sometimes you may share your information publicly, such as by posting on our [Community](https://community.bulb.co.uk/) page or on social media sites. Remember, when you share information publicly it may become accessible through search engines.

### Sending your data outside the European Economic Area

Sometimes our agents and service providers are based outside the European Economic Area, so when working with them, we may pass your information outside of the European Economic Area to countries that do not have the same data protection standards as the UK.

If we do this, we will ensure that any information will be protected in line with this Privacy Policy. Some of the safeguards we rely on to share your information outside the European Economic Area include ensuring that the supplier has, if in the USA (wherever possible), certified to the Privacy Shield.

## You're in control

### Your rights

If we collect or handle your personal data, you have rights as an individual which you can exercise in relation to the information we hold about you:

  * To correct or update your personal information, you can log into your [Bulb Account](https://account.bulb.co.uk/) or your Carbon Calculator account.

  * To delete your personal information, you can email us at [privacy@bulb.co.uk](mailto:privacy@bulb.co.uk). We will delete any information that we no longer need to hold, but we won't always be required to do this. For example, we may need to hold your information to continue to provide your energy under our contract. If this is the case, we'll explain why.

  * To ask us to restrict processing of your personal information or transfer your personal information to a different organisation, you can email us at [privacy@bulb.co.uk](mailto:privacy@bulb.co.uk).

  * To confirm if we are using your personal information or get access to all your personal information that we hold, in an easy to understand, portable and secure format, you can email us at [privacy@bulb.co.uk](mailto:privacy@bulb.co.uk) with the subject line "Subject Access Request".

  * To object to the processing of your personal information, you can email us at [privacy@bulb.co.uk](mailto:privacy@bulb.co.uk).

  * To withdraw consent to process your data, you can email us at [privacy@bulb.co.uk](mailto:privacy@bulb.co.uk) at any time.

  * To opt-out of marketing communications you can email us at [privacy@bulb.co.uk](mailto:privacy@bulb.co.uk).

Once we receive a request from you, we will respond within at most 1 month, but usually a lot quicker. Before actioning these requests, we will need to positively identify you. In line with our [Member Service wait time policy](https://bulb.co.uk/blog/our-swear-jar-keeping-our-phone-and-email-wait-time-promise), we aim to send responses to all emails within an hour.

If you're unhappy with how we've handled or processed your personal information - or you want further information about your rights - you have the right to contact the [Information Commissioner's Office](https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation-gdpr/individual-rights/), the supervisory body that regulates handling of personal information in the UK.

### Keeping your information secure

Whilst we cannot ensure or guarantee that unauthorised access to or unauthorised alteration, disclosure or loss of information will never occur, we work hard to prevent it. In particular:

  * We use encryption to keep your data private while in transit.

  * Your account information is protected for your privacy and security. Either this is through a password you have chosen or you can log-in to your account directly with your email address. Bulb and our agents will never ask for your password.

  * To help keep your account and your personal information secure you should not disclose your password details to anyone. You should also make sure your Bulb account password is different from your email address password. We recommend you change your passwords from time to time.

  * We review our practices for collecting, processing and storing personal information, including physical security measures, to guard against unauthorised access to systems and backups to prevent the loss of information. We will continue to enhance our security procedures as new technology becomes available.

  * We restrict access to personal information wherever possible to people who need to know that information to process it and who are subject to contractual confidentiality requirements.

### Retaining and holding your information

We keep the personal information we collect for no longer than is necessary for the purposes for which we collected it.

The length of time depends on the purposes for which we use it, or otherwise to meet our legal obligations.

We will delete any information as soon as we no longer have a valid reason to hold it. If this is not possible (for example, because your personal information has been stored in backup archives), then we will securely store your personal information and isolate it from any further processing until deletion is possible.

## Contact us

You can get in touch about anything in this Policy by emailing us and our Data Protection Officer at [privacy@bulb.co.uk](mailto:privacy@bulb.co.uk) or by [contacting us](https://help.bulb.co.uk/hc/en-us/articles/115001240291-How-can-I-get-in-touch-with-Bulb-).

## About this Policy

### When this Policy applies:

For the purposes of this Policy, "we", "us", "our" and "Bulb" means Bulb Energy Ltd and other companies in the same group. Unless otherwise stated, Bulb is the Data Controller for your personal data.

This Policy applies to how we use your information in relation to our products and services generally.

This Policy doesn't apply to other companies' sites that you get to through our website or social media pages. So make sure you've read their policy before putting your personal information on their site.

### Changes to this Policy:

We may change this Policy at any time. If we make any changes, we'll post them on this page. If they're substantive changes, we'll also have a more prominent notice letting you know. You can also email or write to us for a physical copy.

Your continued use of our services will mean that you accept and agree to any changes to the Privacy Policy.

 **Last updated:**  The Policy was last updated on 5 December 2019.
